<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Radicalization of LeRoi Jones</title>
    <description>Artifact 3
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 12:56:47 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 12:56:47 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>LeRoi Jones</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;LeRoi Jones was born in 1934 in Newark, New Jersey. Jones’ work spans a large
period of time and styles, mixing avant-garde poetry from the New York School
with radical and often incendiary and politically motivated subtext.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jones had many identities throughout his tenure as a poet and writer. In the
1950s, he was mostly involved with white New York poets like Alan Ginsburg.
However, in the 1960s, his identity and writing began to transform into that
of a Black nationalist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1965, after Malcolm X was assassinated, LeRoi Jones changed his name to
Amiri Baraka and moved to Harlem to form the Black Arts School which was
devoted to developing a new aesthetic for Black Artists, embracing Black
culture as a basis for art, while rejecting white culture’s influence on
their art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His poetry and writing became radical as he incorporated
more racial references in his writing. As he matured further, his identity
shifted into that of a Marxist, blaming capitalism for many of the problems
the Black community faced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2018/04/15/black-magic/&quot;&gt;Next: Black Magic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/amiri-baraka/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/amiri-baraka/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Black Magic</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Black Magic&lt;/em&gt; by Amiri Baraka is a collection of poetry written by Baraka from
the time period of 1961 to 1967. This period of time was a period of transition
in Baraka’s life, as he began to shed his connections to the predominately white
New York School and embraced his Blackness and Black culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baraka separates this volume into 3 books: &lt;em&gt;Sabotage&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Target Study&lt;/em&gt;, and
&lt;em&gt;Black Art&lt;/em&gt;, each thematically representing a time in Baraka’s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sabotage&quot;&gt;Sabotage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first book, &lt;em&gt;Sabotage&lt;/em&gt;, comes early in Baraka’s ouevre. As Baraka says
himself in the preface, his early work represented “a cloud of abstraction
and disjointedness that was just whiteness.” Baraka in this work seems to
attempt to appeal to “whiteness” by sticking to a style similar to the
avant-garde of the New York School. However, Baraka still maintains his
connection to Black culture making several references to race within his
poetry. The piece “Kenyatta Listening to Mozart” juxtaposes his connection
to Africa and Blackness with European Culture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/kenyatta.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kenyatta was an anti-colonial activist in Kenya and became its first Prime
Minister. The title of the poem, “Kenyatta Listening to Mozart”, creates a
juxtaposition between Africa with Kenyatta and the West with Mozart. The
entire poem references this juxtaposition throughout its text. In the first
stanza, Baraka references the American poets in San Francisco, referencing
the Beat writers like Jack Kerouac and Allen Ginsburg that were associated
with San Francisco. In the next stanza, Baraka evokes imagery of Africa with his
references to “brush” and “undergrowth” while also contrasting that with the
imagery of “spats”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This juxtaposition creates an interesting parallel with Baraka’s life. In this
time period, Baraka began to question his roots as a Beats poet, while embracing
his own Blackness. This poem seems to highlight his own personal struggle with
appreciating his enjoyment for Western Art with his desire to become more
involved with a Black Power movement. It could also foreshadow his involvement
Black Nationalistic groups. The reference to Kenyatta could be a reference to
himself as he envisions himself a leader to bring revolution to a people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;target-study&quot;&gt;Target Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baraka described his work on &lt;em&gt;Target Study&lt;/em&gt; as “trying to really study,..less
passive now, less uselessly “literary”…trying to see, trying to understand…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Target Study&lt;/em&gt;, Baraka began to commit to his radical and controversial
style that defined Amiri Baraka. While &lt;em&gt;Sabotage&lt;/em&gt; remained invested in the
tropes common in Avant-Garde poetry, &lt;em&gt;Target Study&lt;/em&gt; mostly took a look at
Black culture. In the piece, “Black Bourgeoisie”, Baraka offers a stinging
commentary on the “Black Bourgeoisie” who Baraka thought had to shed their
internal Black self to appease whites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/black_bourgeois.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title “Black Bourgeoisie” itself is most likely a reference to the book,
&lt;em&gt;Black Bourgeoisie&lt;/em&gt;, published by E. Franklin Frazier, who himself was
referenced by Baraka in &lt;em&gt;Sabotage&lt;/em&gt; in the poem “Letter to E. Franklin Frazier”.
Frazier’s work was extremely controversial at the time since it criticized
middle class Black families that wanted to be accepted in white society by
shedding their own personal identity. Baraka was similarly critical of this
Black Bourgeoisie, stating that his own university, Howard, “let me understand
the Negro sickness. They teach you to pretend to be white.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The poem, “Black Bourgeoisie”, references this criticism throughout the text. On
the surface, members of the Black Bourgeoisie care about the affairs of Black
people, but their real motivations are money and appealing to white people.
Baraka describes this hidden motivation in the double entendre “dreams about
Lincoln(s)”. Baraka references both Abraham Lincoln and both $5 bills with
Lincoln on them. This highlights the hidden motivations. In the last lines of
the poem, he writes that they do “hate ofays / hates, instead, him self / him
black self”. Ofays is a perjorative slang for white people. Baraka criticizes
the Black Bourgeoisie for liking white people instead of themselves and their
identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;black-art&quot;&gt;Black Art&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final book in the collection represents a culmination of conflicting ideas
and themes in Baraka’s work and becomes his most lucid and clear manifesto in
this book about race. As Baraka himself states in the preface,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Black Art&lt;/em&gt; was the crucial seeing, the decisions, the actual move. The
strengthening to destroy, and the developing of willpower to build, even
in the face of destruction and despair, even with, or WITHOUT, the
confrontation of blankness, whiteness, etc.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early poem in the collection, titled “Black Art”, confronts this realization
of the true purpose of his poetry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/black_art1.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/black_art2.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a large way, this poem discusses Baraka’s realization of the true power of
poetry, confronting his critics who claimed that poetry is best done without
the influence of political motivation. Baraka explicitly calls this out in the
first line where he calls poetry without teeth “bullshit”. He wants his poetry
to have power, to fight against the injustices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baraka takes on a much more violent and radical tone in this poetry, unfiltered
and unafraid to take on a force he believes to be unjust. He makes references to 
stealing weapons from cops, pulling their tongues out and leaving them for dead.
This language is much more incendiary and aptly describes Baraka’s controversial
tone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, throughout the course of &lt;em&gt;Black Magic&lt;/em&gt;, themes of race and fighting
for your race become more prominent as both the themes and style of writing
become more incendiary and radical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2017/04/15/tales/&quot;&gt;Next: Tales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/04/15/black-magic/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/04/15/black-magic/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tales</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tales&lt;/em&gt; by Amiri Baraka was a collection of short stories written in 1967. Tales 
focuses more personally on the story of a Black Man living in White America and
later, a Black Man living in Black America. These two experiences together set
the framework for which Tales tells its narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tales&lt;/em&gt; explores several themes are periods of time in a young Black man’s life,
perhaps drawing parallels to his own life. One of the stories in &lt;em&gt;Tales&lt;/em&gt;, “Uncle
Tom’s Cabin: Alternate Ending”, describes a scene where a young Black boy
answers a question a white teacher asked correctly. While this situation seems
not to have significance at first, Baraka describes a fear, or a doctrine
engrained in Black people to not show their true self in the face of White
people. From the text:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“One little black boy, raised his hand, and looking at the tip of Miss Orbach’s
nose said 6 1/2…I would have said “No boy, shut up and sit down. You are
wrong. You don’t know anything. Get out of here and be very quick. Have you no 
idea what you’re getting involved in? My God … you nigger, get out of here
and save youself, while there’s time…””&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite correctly identifying the correct answer, the narrator instantly assumes
the boy’s answer is incorrect and thinks about scolding him for speaking out of
line. Baraka comments on the attitude that Black People would have at the time
of being scared of challenging the status quo or being considered by White
people the stereotype of an “Uppity Negro”. Baraka takes the form of someone so
engrained in the social order that they do not want to challenge the social
order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2016/04/15/archive/&quot;&gt;Next: Archival Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/04/15/tales/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/04/15/tales/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Archival Work</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the late 1960s and 70s, Baraka published several essays and poetry
through a smaller, more obscure publication, “Jihad Publications”. The name is
a reference to the Arabic word, “Jihad”, describing a struggle. However, to
the word Jihad has a connotation of “Holy War”, a connotation that Baraka might
have been trying to exploit to be as radical and revolutionary as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His work under the Jihad Publications ranges from essays on Black Nationalism
to more poetry. One essay, titled “The National Black Assembly and the Black
Liberation Movement”, from the early 70s, highlights Baraka’s radicalism. Here
are some excerpts from the text (the full texts can be found at the bottom of
the page).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blacklib.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite Baraka’s radicalism, and his anger towards whites, he does not place the
sole blame of problems Black people face towards White people; he instead blames
an entire capitalistic system for the exploitation of Black people and other
workers. This text highlights both Baraka’s interest in Black Nationalism while
foreshadowing his eventual turn to Marxism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another essay, “Creating a Unified Conscousness”, Baraka advocates for all
Blacks to join together in revolution. Here is an excerpt:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/con.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baraka’s advocacy for a unified front of Blacks, all joined to overthrow
power is extremely radical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/natblack.pdf&quot;&gt;Download: The National Black Assembly and the Black Liberation Movement&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/unicon.pdf&quot;&gt;Download: Creating a Unified Consciousness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/04/15/archive/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/04/15/archive/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
